# Miguel Xochicale

My research interests are advancing AI tools for Medical Imaging, MedTech, SurgTech, Biomechanics and Clinical Translation.

Research Engineer, advancing AI-based Surgical Navigation tools Advanced Research Computing Centre and WEISS University College London, UK ■ m.xochicale@ucl.ac.uk

A http://mxochicale.github.io · In mxochicale

### **Education**

#### Ph.D. in Computer Engineering at The University of Birmingham

Birmingham, UK

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019. Thesis: 🕻 GitHub: 🖶 Website: 🗹

M.Sc. in Signal Processing at Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE)

Puebla, México

Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers.

Sep 2004 - Sep 2006

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

Awarded MSc degree: 01/11/2006. Thesis: 🚨 GitHub: 🗂

### Research Experience

#### Research Engineer at University College London, UK

Oct 2022 - Present

- Collaborators: Stephen Thompson, Dr Thomas Dowrick and Prof Matt Clarkson
- I am advancing AI-based Surgical Navigation tools with Python and CUDA programming languages via GitHub. See more at ( ).

#### Sep 2021 - Sep 2022 Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging at King's College London, UK

PIs: Dr Andrew King and Dr. Alberto Gomez

I scientifically contributed to automatic biometric recognition of electrocardiography ultrasound data using real-time deep learning techniques with Python, CUDA, C++ and Qt programming languages via GitHub. See more at ( .).

#### Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering at King's College London, UK

Apr 2019 - Aug 2021

- PIs: Dr. Wenfeng Xia and Prof. Tom Vercauteren
- I pushed forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions, contributing to the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system for clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. See more at ( ).

### **Publications**

- T. Dowrick, S. Thompson, M. Clarkson, and M. Xochicale, Open-source software for surgical technologies: A white paper, Jul. 2023.
- M. Iskandar, H. Mannering, Z. Sun, J. Matthew, H. Kerdegari, L. Peralta, and M. Xochicale, "Towards realistic ultrasound fetal brain imaging synthesis," in Medical Imaging with Deep Learning(MIDL '23), arXiv, Apr. 2023, 3 pages, 1 figure with code and data.
- L. Tsz Yan and M. Xochicale, "Towards a simple framework of skill transfer learning for robotic ultrasound-guidance procedures," in Robot-Assisted Medical Imaging (RAMI) ICRA workshop 2023(RAMI '23), arXiv, Apr. 2023, 2 pages, 2 figure with code and data.
- 4. A. Badillo-Perez, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Barco, R. Montenegro, and M. Xochicale, "Teaching ai and robotics to children in a mexican town," in 18th HRI conference at the 2nd Inclusive HRI workshop(HRI '23), arXiv, Mar. 2023, 4-page paper and 2-page appendix with code and data.
- M. Xochicale, L. Thwaites, S. Yacoub, L. Pisani, T. H. N. Phung, H. Kerdegari, A. King, and A. Gomez, A machine learning case study for ai-empowered echocardiography of intensive care unit patients in low- and middle-income countries, Jan. 2023, 4-page pre-print, 2-page appendix, code, data and slides.
- T. Bautista, J. Matthew, H. Kerdegari, L. Peralta, and M. Xochicale, "Empirical study of quality image assessment for synthesis of fetal head ultrasound imaging with dcgans," in 26th UK Conference on Medical Image Understanding and Analysis (MIUA '22), arXiv, Jun. 2022, 3-page abstract, code and data.
- 7. A. Badillo-Perez, D. Badillo-Perez, D. Coyotzi-Molina, D. Cruz, R. Montenegro, L. Vazquez, and M. Xochicale, "Piloting diversity and inclusion workshops in artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 17th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '22), Mar. 2022.
- 8. R. Beale, J. B. Rosendo, C. Bergeles, et al., "Oxvent: Design and evaluation of a rapidly-manufactured covid-19 ventilator," eBioMedicine, vol. 76, p. 103 868, 2022.
- C. Baker, M. Xochicale, F.-Y. Lin, et al., "Intraoperative needle tip tracking with an integrated fibre-optic ultrasound sensor," Sensors, vol. 22, no. 23,
- 10. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in human-humanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.
- 11. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and M. Xochicale, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21), Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 12. C. Baker, M. Xochicale, F. Joubert, et al., "Real-time ultrasonic tracking of an intraoperative needle tip with integrated fibre-optic hydrophone," in 2021 IEEE International Ultrasonics Symposium (IUS), 2021, pp. 1-4.
- 13. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in 5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17), Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 14. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17), Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 15. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in 2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics (WeRob '16), Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 16. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.

### Talks and Posters

- 1. I. Idil Ozdemir, M. Xochicale, and S. Thompson, "Towards sustainable dashboards for open-source software projects," RSLondonSouthEast 2023 at Imperial College London, Jul. 2023, Presentation, Abstract.
- 2. M. Xochicale, "Innovating in medical device development," OxfordXML Seminar, Jun. 2023, Presentation, Abstract.
- M. Xochicale, "Fetal ultrasound imaging synthesis," Data Learning Seminar at Imperial College London, Sep. 2022, Presentation Abstract.
- 4. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in neuromatch 3.0 (NMC3 '20), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation Abstract.
- M. Xochicale, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- 6. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.

July 20, 2023

- 7. M. Xochicale, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in human-humanoid interaction," in 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.
- M. Xochicale, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 9. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

### Supervision and Teaching Experience

#### University College London

Jan 2023 – Present

- Teaching Associate: AI in Healthcare Group project. Lecturer: Prof. Paul Taylor
- I led two group projects on Fetal Brain Ultrasound Imaging synthesis with Diffusion Models.
- Supervision: Xiaoning Zhu, M.Sc in Health Data Science Project: Automatic Medical Image Reporting with transformer-based models. Jan 23' - Aug 23'
- Supervision: Qingyu Yang, M.Sc. in Health Data Science Project: High-resolution Fetal Brain Ultrasound Imaging synthesis with diffusion models. 23' - Aug 23'
- Supervison: Sujon Hekim, in 2 reserach summer placement Project: AI-based surgical skill assessment using transformer model.

June 23' - Aug 23'

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

Feb 2021 - Aug 2022

Oct 2021 - May 2022

Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

Jan 2020 - Sep 2020

Jan 2022 - Apr 2022

Jan 2021 – Apr 2021

Jan 2020 - Apr 2020

2019-Present

Jan 2020 – September 2022

Jan 23' - March 23'

#### King's College London

- Supervision: Pablo Prieto Roca and Samuel Eyob. KURF projects on 3DGANs for fetal US imaging.
- Supervision: Tsz Yan (Goosie) Leung, MSc in Medical Engineering and Physics. Project: Simple US guidance intervention.
- Supervision: Thea Bautista, M. Eng. in Biomedical Engineering. Project: DCGANs for fetal US imaging.
- Supervision: Guilherme Gomes de Figueiredo and Amal Hussein. KURF projects on DCGANs for US imaging. Supervision: Alexander Mitton, M.Sc. in Medical Engineering and Physics. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia.
- Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Alejandro Granados
- Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu
- Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles

#### The University of Birmingham

Jun 2018 - Dec 2018

- Aug 2018 Dec 2018 Supervision: Dinghuang Zhang, M.Sc. in Computer Engineering. Project: Tools for human-humanoid collaboration Aug 2017 - Dec 2017; Jan 2018 - Apr 2018
- Teaching associate: Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Prof. Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony
- Teaching Associate: Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte
- Teaching Associate Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu
- Teaching Associate: Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Prof. Chris Baber

Jan 2017 - Apr 2017

Aug 2016 - Dec 2016; Aug 2017 - Dec 2017 Aug 2016 - Dec 2016

## Grants, Awards and Honours

- My M.Sc. student, Thea Bautista received the Maurice Wilkins Prize at KCL for the best MEng Individual Research Project in 2022 🗹 (30/08/2022).
- King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang 🗹 (07/01/2021 - 07/01/2022)
- My M.Sc. student, Alexander Mitton, won the Outstanding Individual Project award 🗹
- King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration with (14/04/2020 - 9/06/2020)
- "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the 2nd forum of Mexican Talent 2017 🗹 11/01/2017 I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh 🗹 16-18/06/2016
- My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the 1st international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015). 🗹 🗈 20-24/07/2015
- I won a Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology and University of Birmingham. 11/2014-11/2018
- Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME, presenting a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo. 25-27/05/2013

### Skills

July 20, 2023

Programming and software Python[2014-present], GNU/Linux Operating System user (OpenSuse, Debian & Ubuntu)[2005-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016-present], GNU-Octave (as well as MatLab)[2009-present], LATEX[2006-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016-present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], continuous integration & continuous delivery [2019-present], CUDA Programming [2021-present], & pythonbased linting [2022-present].

Tools and hardware Single-board computers and microcontrollers (NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, BeagleBone, Arduino & PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (calibration, collection & data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], Graphic design (Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (Autodesk inventor, blender, FreeCAD, & onshape)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (PyTorch, & TensorFlow)[2017-present], 3D printing (flsun, cura) [2019-present], Video framegrabbers (PCI & usb from ephipan), & Clinical Ultrasound Devices (Voluson E10, Philips EPIC, convex & linear probes), Medical imaging (3D slicer, ITK-SNAP), & NVIDIA Clara AGX

QMS Control documents with standard compliances using: Good Machine Learning Practice by FDA, Health Canada, & MHRA; IEC 62304 Medical Device Software Standard; BS EN 82304-1:2017 Health Software; IEC 60601-1 Medical electrical equipment; BS EN 61391-2:2010 Ultrasonics;, & BSI 60825-14 Safety of laser products.

Languages Spanish[Native], English[Fluent] and interested in learning Chinese.

## Outreach activities and scientific engagement

- Lead organiser of "Open-Source Software for Surgical Technologies" at the Hamlym Symposium on Medical Robotics 2023 🗹 . Jan 23' - Oct 23'.
- Co-organised of journal club for computer vision and deep learning at Advanced Research Computing Centre 01-01-2023 - present.Co-organised of activities for SciKit-Surgery tools for the CMICHACKS hackathon: **\(\mathbb{L}\)**. 10/11-11-2022.
- Co-organised of events at the Early Career Researcher Network at the BMEIS (monthly meetings & writing workshops). 01-01-2021 - 01-09-2022.
- Participation in the Westminster Enterprise Week to engage students aged 14-18 to Biomedical Engineering. 10-11-2021
- Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students aged 14-18 to STEAM 23-03-2021
- Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at BMEIS 02-2020 - 06-2020
- For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist. 20-08-2019
- 09-2019 For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI.
- Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: 
  and GitHub: 05-2018
- 2016 to 2018 Research Poster Conference for (2015) 🗖 , (2016) 🗖 , and (2018) 🗖 . GitHub: 👼
- Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: 👼 . 2014-2018 Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: 🗖 , Website: 🗹 . 2017-2018

Miguel Xochicale · Curriculum Vitae

• Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children. Twitter: 💆 @air4children GitHub: 🖶 @air4children